<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Zions deliverance and her friends duty: or The grounds of expecting, and meanes of procuring Jerusalems restauration. In a sermon preached at a publicke fast, before the Honourable House of Commons. By William Sedgvvicke, minister of Farnham in Essex.</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, William, 1609 or 10-1669?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92869</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E107_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18932</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860503</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860503</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112624</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92869)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 19:E107[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Zions deliverance and her friends duty: or The grounds of expecting, and meanes of procuring Jerusalems restauration. In a sermon preached at a publicke fast, before the Honourable House of Commons. By William Sedgvvicke, minister of Farnham in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, William, 1609 or 10-1669?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 54, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Bellamy, &amp; Ralph Smith, at the three Golden Lyons in Corne-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Final leaf = order to print.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at a fast before the Honourable House of Commons.</note>
                  <note>Late copies have two errors corrected on p. 7: line 19, "Syrus" corrected to "Cyrus"; and line 4 from botton, "Sand-ballet" corrected to "Sanballat".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LXII, 7 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112624:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ZIONS DELIVERANCE AND HER FRIENDS DVTY: OR The Grounds of Expecting, and Meanes of Procuring <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems</hi> Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON PREACHED AT A PVB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LICKE FAST, Before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM SEDGVVICKE, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> FARNHAM <hi>in</hi> ESSEX.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Bellamy, &amp; Ralph Smith,</hi> at the three Golden Lyons in <hi>Corne-hill.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112624:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112624:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable the Houſe of COMMONS, now Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>day of Jacobs trouble</hi> yet continues: Yea, growes more gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and darke; clouds of dangers increaſe, therefore your faith needs all the props, that prayer or Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Pulpit or Preſſe can afford. If God by this Sermon d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d any whit kindle your Zeale, I wiſh you had leaſure to read it; it may adde a mite more to <hi>our treaſury,</hi> Your faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and conſtancy. In this Wilderneſſe your Soules ſhould be fed every day with a portion of ſpirituall Manna, <hi>That you may be ſtrengthened with all might accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his glorious power;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.11.</note> And God may be your arme every morning.</hi> What is good,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.2.</note> let it dwell with you, and by it you in God: No place ſo fit for you in theſe great affaires, and hard difficulties, as <hi>the ſecret of the moſt High.</hi> You have beene happy in conceiving juſt and good propoſals, be ſtrong and faithfull in maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and producing of them: and be not overborne:
<pb facs="tcp:112624:3"/>Chriſt dyed under the ſentence of a Judge that would have went right if the times had not beene bad, that knew how to propoſe, but not to proſecute juſtice; and ſo left but this to poſterity, He would have beene juſt, but was not. That deſerves not the name of a ſingle vertue, that will not indure multiplicity of trials. I know your dangers are great,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.109.110.</note> and your condition as <hi>Davids, My Soule is continually in my hand; they have laid a ſnare for me; Yet erred not I from thy precepts.</hi> Your lives are in your hands; and they are pretious, <hi>A Diadem in the hand of God:</hi> But they are indeed the leaſt of thoſe jewels that you are intruſted with. There is in your hands Gods honour, the Kingdome of Chriſt, Churches, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which you muſt defend and maintaine, if you would have God defend You. You are yet poſſeſſed of a richer Jewell then life, innocency and integrity; Let nothing purchaſe it of You, let no power wreſt it from You: <hi>Nec Caeſar,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 27.5.</note> nec Populus.</hi> Reſolve with <hi>Job, I will not leave mine innocency till I dye.</hi> You are the onely hopefull meanes of our deliverance under heaven, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in the hand of God, in the eye of faith, in the wombe of Prayer, and in the affections of Gods People: my onely adviſe that I ſhall be bold to preſent unto you, is, That You be <hi>Faithfull to the death,</hi> and God will Crowne your labours with a happy ſucceſſe here, and You with a Crowne of life eternally. Thus adviſes, prayes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>he, that if he could be leſſe himſelfe, would be more Gods, the Churches, and Your Servant, WILLIAM SEDGVVICKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112624:3"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached at a Faſt before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH 62.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh, and till he make <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the earth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Prophet in the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapters, foretels the happineſſe, and proſperity of the Church:
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 60.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Glorious light:
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 4, 5, 6.</note> Seas, floods, droves of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts,</hi> and thoſe not ſmall, but great ones;
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>The force of the Gentiles, Kings ſhall come to her light: Holineſſe
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 21.</note> univerſall,</hi> and glorious;
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 61.10.</note> 
               <hi>robes of righteouſneſſe,</hi> together with peace, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over enemies, joy, riches, as you may ſee at large in thoſe two Chapters: So cleare was his faith, and ſo ſtrong his deſires after theſe mercies for <hi>Zion,</hi> that he reſolves upon the meanes of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining them, in the firſt verſe of this Chapter:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112624:4"/>
               <hi>For Zions ſake I will not hold my peace, &amp;c.</hi> Never ceaſe Preaching, Praying, never reſt <hi>Untill the righteouſneſſe thereof goe forth as brightneſſe; and the ſalvation therof as a lampe that burneth:</hi> The more he did force <hi>Zion,</hi> the more God let him ſee what he intended to doe for her. In the 2, 3, &amp; 4. verſes, his expreſſions are higher; <hi>A Crowne of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a royall Diadem in the hand of thy God, Hephzibah, Beulah, &amp;c.</hi> In the 6. verſe the Prophet produces the meanes to effect this great worke, by way of a promiſe: And to render it the more certaine, he utters it in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God, <hi>I;</hi> and in the preterperfect tenſe, <hi>I have; Set Watchmen,</hi> Princes, and Governours, as well as Prophets and Teachers, it is interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of both; <hi>Upon thy walls, O Jeruſalem,</hi> in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and publique place; <hi>Which ſhall never hold their peace;</hi> conſult, labour, pray, uſe all meanes; <hi>Night nor Day,</hi> conſtantly, in good and bad times. And when this ſhould be, the Prophet cals in the helpe of <hi>All that make mention of the Lord,</hi> all that have any intereſt in God, or that make any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his wayes; that they ſhould <hi>not keepe ſilence,</hi> ſhould joyne hearts and hands, doe what they could in their places; and <hi>Give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh, and make Jeruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi> I ſhall open the words firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Give him no reſt,</hi> ſeeke him conſtantly, impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately, indeavour it earneſtly: You may read, <hi>ſilence,</hi> or <hi>reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.12. <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>Silence,</hi> Gods not anſwering our prayers, is in Scripture called <hi>ſilence,</hi> as his anſwering and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112624:4"/>delivering is termed <hi>pleading,</hi> or <hi>ſpeaking;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 50.34. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 74.23.</note> and it notes to us:</p>
            <p>Firſt, the eaſineſſe of delivering the Church by Gods mighty hand; he can as eaſily helpe, as we can ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Juſtice of God in delivering his people; it is as pleading, ſhewing the right diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the truth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the naturall and conſtant effect of Prayer; we ſpeake to God by Prayer, he anſwers by ſaving us: our language to him is Prayer, his language to us, is Salvation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But our tranſlation reades it <hi>reſt; Give him no reſt:</hi> There is no paſſion in God properly, neither reſt nor motion; but the Scripture holds forth God to us in theſe tropicall expreſſions for our underſtanding. When God doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſave his people, he is ſaid to <hi>forget,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 44.23.</note> and then his people are termed his <hi>remembrancers:</hi> ſometimes he is ſaid to <hi>ſleepe,</hi> and then his people <hi>awaken</hi> him: Sometimes to be ſlow, or delay, and then wee muſt quicken him, <hi>make no tarrying:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 40.17.</note> Sometimes God ſeemes to loſe his mercy, and then his people muſt finde it for him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.15.</note> 
               <hi>Where is thy zeale, and thy ſtrength, and the ſounding of thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels?</hi> And here he ſeemes to reſt till he be diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted by our prayers; as if he were paſſive to our prayers; as if he could not but helpe when we ſeeke. The reaſon of this expreſſion is to ſhew,</p>
            <p>Firſt, the neceſſity of prayer. God will give, <hi>But for all theſe things I will be ſought unto:</hi> God will come, but he will have his peoples prayers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112624:5"/>lead him into the field,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>I came for thy Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to ſtirre us up to importunity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, that although God ſeeme to deny, to be unwilling to helpe, yet we ſhould follow him cloſe, <hi>Give him no reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, to ſhew the certaine power and effect of prayer; it is as certaine, as if God could not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>withſtand its force: God ſayes to <hi>Moſes, Let me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, Exod.</hi> 32.10.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, to honour this ordinance of Prayer; when God would give us a mercy, he gives it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hand of prayer, and prayer ſhall ſeeme to doe that which he intends.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, it notes the infallibility of the Churches deliverance; as God cannot alwayes reſt, ſo his Church ſhall not alwayes ſuffer: God muſt <hi>ariſe,</hi> and then <hi>his enemies muſt be ſcattered. Pſal.</hi> 68.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Till he eſtabliſh,</hi> till he make firme. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſuppoſes the worke might meete with dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and oppoſitions; the foundations might be laid, and ſuffer many ſhakings before it could be eſtabliſht, therefore he exhorts them to conſtancy till the worke were eſtabliſht.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And untill Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some interpret <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> literally. And of thoſe, ſome looke upon the promiſe fulfilled, <hi>viz.</hi> by Chriſts comming in the fleſh; <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was then a praiſe in the earth, when our Saviour, the Lord of all,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.2.3.</note> was in it. And it cannot be denyed but it was in ſome part fulfilled then: for Chriſt applying part of this Propheſie to himſelfe in his owne times, ſayes, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.21. <hi>This day is this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112624:5"/>Scripture fulfilled in your eares.</hi> And ſo in part it was. But the chiefe and maine of this, and the reſt is yet to come, as we ſhall ſee anon. Others underſtand it according to the letter, but as to come, and ſo expect the calling of the Jewes to a happy eſtate in their owne Country, that they ſhall againe inhabit <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> but this is ſubject to controverſie, and therefore we will wave it; and take it in a ſecond ſenſe, myſtically, <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> for the Church; and this is moſt generall, and warranted by Scripture; in which it is very common to call the Church of the Gentiles <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> and <hi>Zion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A praiſe in the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church is ſo; Firſt, when the deliverance of the Church is eminent and notable, ſuch as <hi>All the ends of the earth doe ſee her ſalvation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 98.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, when the Church derives her light to the world, and when the Law,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110.2.</note> the <hi>red of ſtrength goes out of Zion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, and moſt fully, when through out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proſperity, and inward ſpirituall purity, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> ſhould be the beauty of the earth, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the praiſe of the earth; have an eminency of proſperity above all the world.</p>
            <p>The generall parts are two:</p>
            <p>Firſt, mercies to be obtained; And they are of two ſorts: Firſt, Eſtabliſhing mercies, <hi>till he eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh.</hi> Secondly, Perfecting mercies, <hi>make Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem the praiſe of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the meanes to obtaine theſe mercies; <hi>Give him no reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:112624:6"/>
            <p>We will not trouble you with any ſubdiviſion, but caſt our diſcourſe into theſe three points.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Church in the beginnings of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance is ſubject to dangerous ſhakings, <hi>till he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the Church of right is, and in time ſhall be a praiſe in the earth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, every one that makes mention of the Lord, muſt give him no reſt, till this be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</p>
            <p>We ſhall handle the firſt briefely, and by way of Preface; the ſecond, as the maine point; and the third, as the application of the ſecond.</p>
            <p>The Church in the beginnings of her delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, is ſubject to dangerous ſhakings. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet layeth forth the Church to us in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in this place: Here was ſomething done, wals built, and watch-men upon them, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Prophets, labouring their utmoſt, night and day, in Counſelling, Preaching, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but all they did was in danger, enemies ready to ſurpriſe them and their worke, they could take no reſt night nor day; what they had was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, and that little ready to be loſt, ſo is it often with the Church, it riſes through many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and mighty oppoſitions, and her begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of deliverance, many times ſeeme worſe then her loweſt ſufferings. Such was <hi>Iſraels</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from <hi>Egypt:</hi> it was long in, and difficult while they were in <hi>Egypt:</hi> Nothing but ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, plots, taxations, to weaken and ruine them: after <hi>Moſes</hi> appeared, their burthens were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112624:6"/>increaſed; after leave to depart, many changes and uncertainties: ſometimes <hi>Pharaoh</hi> will let them goe, ſometimes not. The laſt deſigne upon them worſt of all, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> raiſed Armes againſt them. After that great deliverance through the redſea; they were forty yeares in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, beſet with many wants; they want bread, and they want water, and which was worſt, they wanted faith, and patience; they murmure, and are weary of their deliverance, <hi>Let us goe backe to Egypt:</hi> And of their Deliverer, <hi>We know not what is become of this Moſes:</hi> and weary of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Let us make us new gods.</hi> They were beſet with enemies on all ſides, <hi>Amalek, Moab, Og,</hi> figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting enemies, plotting enemies, conjuring ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and ſometimes their ſins made God their enemy, he fought againſt them with fiery ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, Plagues. <hi>Iſraels</hi> deliverance from <hi>Babylon,</hi> was as full of oppoſition. <hi>Syrus</hi> makes Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation for the re-building the Temple, <hi>Ezra</hi> 1. the worke is taken in hand, an Altar ſet up, the foundations laid, offerings frequented, Worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men prepared: ſome adverſaries that offered their helpe being refuſed, ſeduce the King by their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill counſell; and then the Reformation is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Rebellion, they are commanded to ceaſe, and the worke reſts till the ſecond of <hi>Darius. Ezra</hi> 4. <hi>ult.</hi> In <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time, what threatning, Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and ſcoffing was practiſed by <hi>Sand-ballet,</hi> and <hi>Tobiah?</hi> ſome of the Nobles were wrought off from the worke, and proved treacherous. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> 6.11. and yet God carryed on the worke
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112624:7"/>through many difficulties. When Chriſt came with ſalvation into the world, all <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was troubled, and <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od</hi> their King, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.3. a deſperate wickedneſſe was preſently practiſed; <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> that he might kill Chriſt, commands that all the male children ſhould be killed: and ſo their condition was worſe then before; they loſt both their King and their children. When he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his Miniſtery, what new Doctrine was Preached? <hi>Never man taught as he taught.</hi> What miracles were wrought? the whole City receive and embrace their Saviour, crying <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> with ſuch Joy and chearefulneſſe, as if Heaven would preſently come to the earth: but quickly after, the people ſeduced by the Scribes and Phariſees, cryes as bitterly, <hi>Crucifie him, Crucifie him:</hi> He is betrayed, accuſed, condemned, crucifyed, and buryed; all ſteps to our deliverance.</p>
            <p>The reaſons of this point are briefly theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God hath no more then he gets by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and that out of the hands of many migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and malignant enemies, which never give up power to Chriſt, but with much ſtriving.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God ſuffers difficulties to come in the way, to manifeſt his owne power, that he is able to carry on his worke through the ſtrongeſt oppoſition.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God doth it to fit us for mercies: what we gaine with difficulty we highly prize, and what we eaſily obtaine, we ſoone deſpiſe. As God fits us for mercies, ſo the mercies for us; things of greateſt excellency are longeſt under
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112624:7"/>the hammer and file; the choyceſt bleſſings muſt paſſe through the fire of affliction.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God ſuffers it for the tryall of his people. When the Church proſpers, ſhe ſhall have many followers more then true friends: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ſends a <hi>Sword to pierce, that the thoughts of many hearts may be diſcovered,</hi> as <hi>Simeon</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.35. Therefore are the tryals God brought upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, called provings, <hi>I have proved thee at the waters of Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, Pſalm.</hi> 81.7. In great undertakings God doth as he did by <hi>Gideons</hi> Army: there was thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand armed againſt <hi>Midian, Judges</hi> 7. God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged as many as were fearefull; twenty two thouſand upon ſecond thoughts were wiſer then to venture themſelves againſt ſuch an enemy, and depart, and yet the people are too many, God hath an other diſcovering device in the 5. and 6. verſes, they that lay downe or bowed themſelves to drinke, men of low ſpirits given to ſatisfie their bellies; or as ſome conjecture, they that had uſed to bow to <hi>Baal,</hi> and had not forgot their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, but bowed to drinke, God would have none of them; onely three hundred active men, that lapt their water, they were fit for the ſervice. So God many times ſuffers the tree of the Church to be ſhaken, that rotten fruite may drop off. To build <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is an honourable ſervice, onely choyce ſpirits ſhall have the dignity to have their hands in it.</p>
            <p>To apply this a little,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> Let not the preſent troubles ſeeme ſtrange to you. We could not expect to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112624:8"/>finde the Dragon aſleepe, and ſo ſteale away the golden fleece of Reformation: neither could we imagine that ſo many cages of uncleane Birds, ſuch beds of Snakes, ſuch neſts of Waſpes, ſhould ſuffer the Refiners fire with patience and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; or that ſuch heapes of idle and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Miniſters, ſuch ſwarmes and hives of Papiſts, ſuch dunghils of prophaneneſſe, ſuch mighty <hi>Nimrods</hi> and devouring oppreſſours, ſhould ſuffer themſelves to be diſpoſſeſſed without reſiſtance and oppoſition. It is with us as it was with the mans ſonne, <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.26. When our Saviour came to caſt out the dumbe and deafe ſpirit, <hi>The Devill rent him ſore, and laid him as dead, till Jeſus tooke him by the hand:</hi> So is it with us, there have been ſome attempts to caſt out the dumbe and deafe ſpirit of this Kingdome; but now Chriſt comes to doe it indeed, he raves, and teares, and foames, and blaſphemes, ſhakes the very pillars of the Kingdome, crackes the foundation of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and threatens confuſion to the whole; but we hope by the helpe of Chriſts hands, the iſſue will be good. God ſeldome doth great things without great commotions. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were delivered, but there was an Earthquake, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.26. When the two witneſſes were raiſed, the two Teſtaments ſet up to guide mens lives, and to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne the Church (as ſome;) or the faithfull Preachers of the Word reſtored to their office, and liberty (as others;) there was an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.13. When Antichriſt fals, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Earthquake, <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.18. and therefore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112624:8"/>though we grieve to ſee it, we could not expect our Reformation without earth-quakes, Church-quakes, and Kingdome-quakes.</p>
            <p>Let it ſtirre you up, as to expect,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> ſo to prepare for difficulties: Let oppoſition double, and not weaken your reſolutions. Noble and generous diſpoſitions are confirmed and exaſperated by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. Take heed of forſaking a good cauſe for bad enemies: that is apparent, your cauſe the beſt, your enemies the worſt, which is ſufficient encouragement. It were madneſſe to leape out of the ſhip, becauſe the windes blow; or to forſake the Church, becauſe of ſome dangers: while you ſtand, the devill and wicked men are your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, if you turne, God and the prayers of his people will be upon the backe of you. If Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth ſhould make warre, there would be no corner of the world ſo ſafe, as on Gods, and the Churches ſide. In the midſt of dangers looke upon feare with <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> eyes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehe.</hi> 6.13.</note> as a reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſinne; we may incourage you, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did his fearefull ſhipmaſter in a ſtorme, <hi>Feare not, thou carryeſt Caeſar and all his fortunes:</hi> So ſay I to you, Feare not, you carry Chriſt, his Ordinances, his People, and their liberties. <hi>David</hi> incourages himſelfe upon the ſame ground, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 46. <hi>I will not feare though the earth be removed, and though the mountaines be carryed into the midſt of the Sea, though the waters thereof roare and be troubled, though the mountaines ſhake with the ſwelling thereof.</hi> His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort was verſe 5. <hi>God is in the midſt of her, ſhe ſhall not be moved.</hi> Therefore, if ſtormes ariſe, doe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112624:9"/>not leſſen your courage, but double your skill and diligence. The Arke, though toſſed a while, will at laſt find a mount <hi>Ararat</hi> to reſt upon. The Churches deliverance was never the further for Chriſts ſufferings, but the nearer. When the <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage grew heavy, <hi>Moſes was borne in that time, Act.</hi> 7.20. When God ſmote <hi>Jacob</hi> that he halted, he quickly bleſſed him: the more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and violent the affliction be, the more ſudden the deliverance; therefore hold up your ſpirits, <hi>He that faints in the day of adverſity, his ſtrength is but ſmall. Amalek</hi> fights, <hi>Moſes</hi> prayes; the wicked rage, the godly beleeve; the devils ſtorme, but Chriſt holds the ſterne. Let the malicious Deſignes of your enemies ſtirre you up to ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe, and unity. Take the Apoſtles counſell, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.27, 28. <hi>Stand faſt in one ſpirit, with one mind, ſtriving together for the faith of the Goſpel; and in nothing terrified by your adverſaries, which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of Salvation, and that of God.</hi> Would you give us an evident ſigne of our approaching deliverance, it would be as an Oracle of God; your undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſtedfaſtneſſe. Nothing can more comfort the good, and diſcomfort the evill, then this; and the more you are oppoſed, the more unite: Give me leave to preſent our requeſts unto you in the Apoſtles following words, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies, fulfill our Joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love. being of one accord, of one minde; Let
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112624:9"/>nothing be done through ſtrife, or vaine-glory.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more acceptable to us, then your u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity; nothing more grievous then the thoughts of diviſion. And while oppoſition hath this effect, to confirme and unite you; it will be, (as it hath beene) to your and our advantage. Nothing is more cleare and manifeſt, that it is with you, as it was with the Apoſtle, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.12. <hi>The things which happened unto me, have falne out rather to the furtherance of the Goſpell:</hi> So what ever hath beene done againſt you, hath beene to the ſhame of the practiſers: So beleeve, they can plot nothing but their owne miſchiefe; <hi>No wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon formed againſt Zion ſhall proſper.</hi> God hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath, and we hope ſtill will make that your portion that was a part of <hi>Joſephs</hi> bleſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.23, 24. <hi>The Archers have ſorely grieved you, and ſhot at you, and hated you: but your bow hath yet abode in ſtrength, and the armes of your hands were made ſtrong, by the hands of the mighty God of Jacob: from thence is the ſhepherd, the ſtone of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ſecond point is, the Church of right is, and in time ſhall be a praiſe in the earth. The Church is called <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.1, 2. <hi>The City of God,</hi> the place of Gods reſidence; <hi>the Mountaine of Holineſſe, Beautifull for ſcituation, the joy of the whole Earth.</hi> And in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.2. <hi>She is tearmed the perfection of beauty;</hi> a high expreſſion, and intended to the Church under the Goſpel, for in that <hi>Pſalme,</hi> God rejects Jewiſh worſhip. So great ſhall be the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of the Church, that it is called <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the Saints in the Church are ſaid to <hi>dwell in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112624:10"/>Heaven, Rev.</hi> 13.6. For the opening and proving of the point, we ſhall,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Shew what this glory is, and wherein it conſiſts.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Prove that this of right belongs to the Church.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That this happineſſe is yet to come.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That upon probable conjecture, we may hope that it is now a comming.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the opening of the firſt, What this praiſe or beauty is. It is not that whoriſh paint, nor carnall pompe, nor that ſtately Tyranny, which adornes the man of ſinne. You may ſee great preparations of this in the two former Chapters, but the conſummation is expreſt in the beginning of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>This praiſe or beauty, is expreſſed generally in Chap. 60. ver. 1.19. <hi>The glory of the Lord is riſen upon thee,</hi> it is ſomething that is divine. <hi>God is the excellency of Jacob, Amos</hi> 8.7. God conferres upon the Church ſpirituall bleſſings, ſuch as are heavenly and Divine in their Nature; and he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferres temporall bleſſings upon his Church; yet ſo as they have upon them the impreſſe of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Almighty hand.</p>
            <p>The particulars of a Churches beauty and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Cleare and ſhining light, Chap. 60. verſe 1, 2.19. God hath promiſed a large increaſe of light, <hi>The light of the Moone ſhall be as the light of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112624:10"/>the Sunne, and the light of the Sunne ſevenfold.</hi> The Church ſhall have <hi>A Crowne of twelve ſtars, be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the Sunne, and the Moone under her feet,</hi> ſhe ſhall have light in all parts.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This light ſhall prevaile and ſpread, abundance ſhall come unto it, multitudes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, Chap 60. ver. 5, 6.8. They are compared to the flowing of the Sea, to droves, to a cloud, to Doves flying, to the windes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Not onely many, but great ones ſhall be converted to the Church, <hi>Kings ſhall come to thy brightneſſe,</hi> Chap. 60. ver. 3. And, <hi>the forces of the Gentiles ſhall come unto thee,</hi> ver. 5. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſucke the breaſts of Kings,</hi> ver. 16. Kings ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the life and ſweetneſſe of their royalties to the helpe of the Church.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Upon theſe he will powre out holl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and that univerſally; <hi>Thy people ſhall be all righteous,</hi> Chap. 60. ver. 21. her <hi>Exactors,</hi> her ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry enemies ſhall be holy, Chap. 60. ver. 17. As univerſall, ſo excellent holineſſe; compared to Robes, Ornaments, Jewels, Chap. 61. ver. 10. by theſe ſpirituall bleſſings ſhe differs from the ſinke and Synagogue of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, To theſe ſpirituall, God will adde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny outward and temporal bleſſings to the Church; Abundance of peace, Chap. 60. ver. 11. <hi>Her gates ſhall be open continually.</hi> Victory over Enemies, <hi>The Nation and Kingdome that will not ſerve thee, ſhall periſh; Yea, thoſe Nations ſhall be utterly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted</hi> Chap. 60. ver. 12. And, <hi>All thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed thee, ſhall bow downe themſelves at the ſole of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112624:11"/>thy feet,</hi> ver. 14. Abundance of Riches, <hi>The glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Lebanon,</hi> ver. 13. <hi>for Braſſe, Gold; for Iron, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver;</hi> ver. 17. and for griefe, joy and rejoycing. But all theſe are but as preparations: the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Churches happineſſe, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, is expreſſed in this Chapter, ver. 3. She ſhall be a <hi>Crowne of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a royall Diadem in the hand of thy God,</hi> ver. 4. <hi>Thou ſhalt be called Hephzipah, and thy Land Beulah, for the Lord delighteth in thee, and thy Land ſhall be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed.</hi> Which is not meant onely of a myſticall and ſpirituall union of the Church to Chriſt, but of a viſible, outward, and manifeſt declaration of this marriage: Chriſt will take his Church by the hand, and publickely owne his people.</p>
            <p>She ſhall be <hi>a Crowne of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a royall Diadem in the hand of thy God,</hi> ver. 3. Chriſt and his Church will ſtand openly hand in hand: there ſhall be a publicke ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nization of <hi>the marriage of the Lambe, Revel.</hi> 19.7. When the Church ſhall ſay, <hi>Loe this is our God, we have waited for him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.9.</note> and he will ſave us.</hi> As his people ſhall ſee it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.5.</note> ſo the world ſhall acknowledge it, and ſay, <hi>Thy Maker is thy Husband.</hi> Men ſee it darkely now,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.2.3.</note> and hate them; but they ſhall ſee it clearely, and honour them. <hi>Satan ſhall be bound and caſt into the bottomleſſe pit,</hi> and with him this Antichriſtian malignity, whereby men oppoſe the wayes of God. Wicked men ſhall be as much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Saints in power as in deſert: they are dogs, and as dogges ſhall they crouch, and <hi>bow to the ſoles of the feet</hi> of Gods children, and <hi>ſhall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112624:11"/>call them the City of the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>chap.</hi> 60.14.</note> the Zion of the holy one of Iſrael.</hi> They ſhall be as honourable as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> was in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court, they ſaid, <hi>Can we find ſuch a man as this is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.38.</note> a man in whom the ſpirit of God is? The righteous is more excellent then his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> now, and will be much more, when God ſhall powre out more of himſelfe upon his ſervants, and this deſperate hatred of Gods people ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the world: Then <hi>ſhall ten men of all lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, take hold of the skirt of him that is a Jew,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.23.</note> ſaying, we will goe with you, for we have heard that God is with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Men ſhall ſay, <hi>Vercly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.11.</note> there is a reward for the righteous, there is a God that judgeth the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſhall be the happy condition of the Church; and this I conceive to be a <hi>PRAISE IN THE EARTH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Our ſecond thing is to prove that this inward and outward happineſſe, of right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Church, and that in time ſhe ſhall and muſt enjoy it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We will take the riſe of our reaſons from the laſt and greateſt happineſſe of the Church; ſhe is the Spouſe of Chriſt, and herefore, the higheſt honour, riches, ſafety, and all excellent priviledges are due to her. She is the Kings wife, dignified with the title of Queene, and Chriſt will give her ſtate and honor ſutable to her place:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.9. <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.8.</note> ſhe is <hi>blacke</hi> with perſecution, her <hi>vaile</hi> and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments rent from her.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>The Daughters ſhall ſee her and bleſſe her; the Queenes and the Concubins ſhall praiſe her. She ſhall be faire as the moone, cleare as the Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112624:12"/>
            <p>Secondly, The Church is the City of God, the mountaine of the Lord, his owne lot, inheritance, portion, and treaſure; expreſſions uſuall in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and all engage God to adorne, furniſh, and beautify his Church he promiſes. Chap. 60. ver. 13. <hi>To beautify the place of his ſanctuary,</hi> and to <hi>make the place of his feet glorious:</hi> his owne <hi>ſanctuary</hi> ſet apart for himſelfe; and the <hi>place of his feete,</hi> where he walkes for his delight and pleaſure, that muſt have ſome ſpeciall beauty and glory beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. It is the Kings palace and Court, there he hath put his name, there is he knowne, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord hath choſen Zion, he hath deſired it for his habitation; This is my reſt for ever, here will I dwell for ever, for I have deſired it.</hi> Every one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to inrich their owne inheritance; ſo will God his.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God hath given Chriſt to his people, and in him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32.</note> and with him all things. That love that gave a Chriſt, <hi>how can he deny us any thing?</hi> that love that was ſo large as to give us the Lord of all, the poſſeſſor, will give us the poſſeſſed. The Apoſtle argues a good title the Church hath to all from this ground, <hi>All are yours, you are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.23. God will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes keepe his people in a bare title, and aright, we ſhall in time <hi>receive the promiſe,</hi> the things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20.23.</note> Chriſt is given as the firſt fruits now, we ſhall have the harveſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Saints are the <hi>heires of the earth,</hi> often ſtiled ſo in Scripture; and the heire of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily is the prayſe, the chiefe. For him are all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112624:12"/>things kept; The world is upheld for the Saints: if they were out of it, God would ſpeedily ruin it, as he did Sodom when <hi>Lot</hi> was out of it. It is given to Chriſt for his uſe to bring up his people in it, and <hi>he upholds it by the word of his power:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.</note> and when his worke is finiſh'd he will take downe this ſtage, it is kept up for their ſakes, and ſhall have its period when they are fit for it; <hi>Thoſe dayes ſhall be ſhortned for the elects ſake, Matth.</hi> 24.21. as that place is ordinarily underſtood of the end of the world: yea now although all men have a right to theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, yet God in the diſpenſation of them hath a ſpeciall reſpect to his people. <hi>Egypt</hi> had the plenty of corne, and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to teach them the right uſe of that plenty, but <hi>Ioſeph</hi> by faith ſaw it was for <hi>Iacobs</hi> poſterity; <hi>God</hi> (ſayes he to his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) <hi>ſent me before you to preſerve you a poſterity in the earth, and to ſave your lives by a great deliverance;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 45 7.</note> Egypt</hi> was <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſtore-houſe: <hi>Cyrus</hi> was advanced, <hi>for Jacob my ſervants ſake, Iſai.</hi> 45.4. ſo all the Kingdomes of the world pay a ſecret tribute to the Churches, and are intruſted as Guardians for the Saints in whom the inheritance is, and he will one day call them to an account.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>God delights in the proſperity of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Pſal.</hi> 35.27. As Princes delight to heape ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours upon their favourites, ſo God takes pleaſure in the greatneſſe as well as in the goodneſſe of his ſervants: he ſuffers in our afflictions, and rejoyces in our deliverances, <hi>In al our afflictions he is afflicted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9.</note> he ſympathizes with his Children if they are diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he is reſtles, he is not ſatisfied, til his people are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112624:13"/>ſatisfied, and <hi>ſee their deſires upon their enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, Gods honour and his peoples proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſtand and fall together: when his Church ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, himſelfe and his name is reproach'd; this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, we may wonder that God hath indured his glory and people to be trampled upon thus long: God hath reſolved to advance his name, and will not ſuffer another to weare it, therefore he will pull downe his enemies, whoſe power and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſtands upon his glory.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, The Church muſt reſemble Chriſt, as in his ſufferings, ſo in his reſurrection: Chriſt communicates his death to his people two wayes; to their ſoules in mortification, and to their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man in affliction: &amp; ſo his reſurrection is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to their ſoules in vivification or holines, and to their outward man in deliverance: <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live, together with my dead body ſhall they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe. Iſa.</hi> 26.19. And <hi>thy dew is as the dew of herbes, and the earth ſhall caſt out her dead,</hi> The Church hath its winter of humiliation, it ſhall have its ſpring of deliverance, and its ſummer of proſperity and happineſſe,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Our third worke is to prove, that this happineſſe is yet to come. And this we ſhall cleare by Scripture, by Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. The Apoſtle there ſpeaking of Chriſt, foretels that he muſt <hi>put downe all rule, and all authority, and power, i.e.</hi> all his enemies, be they of <hi>rule,</hi> the higheſt degree; of <hi>authority,</hi> the middle or ſecond degree; or of <hi>power,</hi> the loweſt and meaneſt; all muſt be ſubject
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112624:13"/>to Chriſt; which the ſame Apoſtle ſpeakes cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of, as yet to come. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.8. <hi>But now we ſee not yet all things put under him:</hi> now the body cannot proſper till the head rules; the wife flouriſh till the husband raignes, nor are Chriſts enemies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his owne feet, till they are under the feet of his Church too.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Two reaſons further yet cleare it.</head>
               <p>Firſt, The Church never yet enjoyed this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity. Chriſt as yet hath appeared in a meane and deſpicable way, as in his perſon, ſo in his Church: both have beene alway buryed, as it were under reproach and perſecution: ſufferings have hitherto beene the Churches portion, firſt, from the Jewes, then from <hi>Rome</hi> heatheniſh, and now from <hi>Rome</hi> antichriſtian. Or if the Church hath had ſome breathing times of peace in ſome parts, they were but ſhort fits, of no continuance; and therefore not the proſperity here foreſpoken of, which is to be <hi>eſtabliſhed,</hi> as a Sun that ſhould never ſet, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 60.20.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The happineſſe here promiſed muſt be both to Jewes and Gentiles, as appeares in the two former Chapters, or at leaſt to the Gentiles by the calling of the Jewes. The Churches ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her light, may be a meanes of the Jewes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, but the Jews converſion ſhall perfect the Churches light and happineſſe.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15.</note> This is foretold <hi>What ſhall the receiving of them be, but life from the dead?</hi> It is true, the Church hath had ſome riches
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112624:14"/>but it hath beene from the fall and diminiſhing of the Jewes, as verſ. 12. But God hath reſerved her perfect happineſſe for the times of their reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which compared with her condition now ſhall be as life from the dead. <hi>Amos</hi> prophecying of this happineſſe, foretels it ſhall be then when he ſhall <hi>Raiſe up the Tabernacle of David that is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ames.</hi> 9.11.12.</note> i.e.</hi> bring in the Jewes: for then ſhall they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe <hi>the remnant of Edom,</hi> the Gentiles that yet lye out, <hi>and the Heathen that are called by my name,</hi> thoſe that are already come in: and when theſe ſhall be poſſeſſed by the Jewes, then will God for altogether cloſe up all breaches, and raiſe up all ruines, and ſo eſtabliſh them together, the praiſe of the earth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Churches happineſſe muſt ſucceed Antichriſts ruine: as <hi>Babylon</hi> fals, ſo ſhall <hi>Zion</hi> riſe, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.21, 22. <hi>He prevailed againſt them till the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of dayes came; and judgement was given to the Saints of the moſt High, and the time came that the Saints poſſeſſed the Kingdome.</hi> Antichriſt now ſits in the temple of God, and keepes out the Church, Chriſt muſt diſpoſſeſſe him, before the Saints ſhall be poſſeſſed of the Kingdome. The whore is firſt judged, and then follow Halelujahs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.1. The firſt is yet to come, and ſo by conſequence, the latter: ſo much power as he hath, ſo much miſery the Church lyeth under.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Our fourth worke is to cleare that the time of this happineſſe is now approaching, that that Sunne is ariſing, that ſhall not goe downe againe.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.20.</note> We doe not undertake determinately to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112624:14"/>demonſtate any thing, <hi>Times and ſeaſons are in the Fathers hands;</hi> but ſhall onely endevour to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſome probable conjecturall grounds that God hath afforded for the quickning our faith, and the encouraging of our hope. As,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That abundance of the ſpirit of prayer, that God hath in theſe times powred out upon his people, much praying certainely prognoſticates ſome ſpeciall mercy: God doth not ſet his people to pray, but when he intends to give. When the 70. yeares were accompliſhed, and deliverance preſently to be wrought, then he ſet <hi>Daniel</hi> on praying, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.2, 3. He prayed before, but then he was ſet on to pray. And this was not the frame of <hi>Daniels</hi> ſpirit onely, but of all the people of God in thoſe times, as God foretold by <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> it ſhould be, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.12, 13. <hi>Then ſhall ye call upon me, and ye ſhall goe and pray unto me, and I will hearken unto you; And ye ſhall ſeeke me and find me, when ye ſhall ſearch for me with all your heart.</hi> Though they had prayed before, yet they ſhould pray now as they had not done before, there ſhould be ſomewhat peculiar in thoſe prayers, they ſhould <hi>goe,</hi> and doe it with <hi>all their hearts.</hi> And doe not the people of God in theſe times pray, as though they were even ſet on to it by God? Are there not gone forth Armies of prayers ſteeled with faith and bold importunity, that are not daunted with the greateſt difficulties? Are there not thouſands that are reſolved, neither to reſt themſelves nor give God any reſt, till Chriſt is upon the throne and his enemies under his feet?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112624:15"/>And therefore ſurely our bondage begins to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, when his people ſhake off the ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and having received the ſpirit of adoption, have learned to cry <hi>Abba,</hi> Father.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The multitude and continuall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of converts; a comfortable fore-runner of a riſing condition, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.17. <hi>When the time of the promiſe drew nigh, the people grew and multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Egypt.</hi> Cutting of ſtones, and hewing of timber is a ſigne God is about to build, not to pull downe. God doth not uſe to <hi>beget children to the murtherer,</hi> nor encreaſe his fold to fat the ſword of his enemies. When God is framing judgements <hi>He takes away his people from the evill to come;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1.</note> It is barrenneſſe preſages deſtruction, but when he takes away their barrenneſſe, he takes away their ſhame, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.2, 3, 4. When the Church hath many children,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.5.</note> ſhe <hi>ſhall not be afraid of her enemies in the gate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, The multitude of active and publicke ſpirits, when God ſets Watchmen upon the wals, he entends not his people for a prey to their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. It is not ordinary for God to raiſe up ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar meanes, and then to blaſt it, nor to ſet up <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Phineas</hi> in the gap to ſave his people, and then to trample upon them. Spirits zealouſly affecting the honour of God, and the good of his people, are too precious to be loſt. There is good hope we are going out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> when the <hi>Hee-goates goe before the Floches;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 50.8.</note> men of publicke place and authority are active for reformation. When the <hi>Governours of Iſrael offer themſelves wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.9.</note>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:112624:15"/>among the people,</hi> there is bleſſing at hand.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The lights encreaſe. This alſo is a ſigne of deliverance, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.4. <hi>Many ſhall run to and fro, and knowledge ſhall be encreaſed:</hi> when the end ſhould come, then this ſhould be. There is much darkeneſſe remaines among us, but the light ſcatters, and daily more ſtanes appeare in our firmament, and the truth as readily embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as it is diſperſed. The morning beginnes to dawne, and we hope it <hi>will ſhine to perfect day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, We may read deliverance in the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies rage, their wickedneſſe ſpeakes the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches mercy: Their deſtruction and the Churches ſalvation ripen together with their ſins. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils rage when it is violent, it is not long, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Rejoyce ye heavens, i.e.</hi> the Saints; <hi>Woe to the inhabitants of the Earth, and of the Sea, i. e.</hi> the wicked and ungodly: <hi>For the devill is come downe having great wrath.</hi> What? can this be matter of joy? Yes, becauſe he <hi>hath but a ſhort time. Men that reſiſt the truth ſhall proceed no further, when their folly becomes manifeſt to all men,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8, 9. When mens wickedneſſe makes them publicke fooles, it will not prevaile much longer. When mens wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe is ſo notorious that the world can point them out, then Gods judgement will quickly find them out. And ſuch are there in our times: ſo helliſh is their malice, their oathes, their blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that they are become an abhorring to men; and therefore ſurely God will ere long caſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his Church of them: doubtleſſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill rides his ſervants ſo furiouſly, that they will
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112624:16"/>quickely be at their journeyes end.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The ſhaking of the Germaine Empire, that great Bulwark of the beaſt, ſpeakes the wrath of God bordering upon the man of ſin. It is neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then a borderer: God hath powred out ſome wrath upon the very Throne of the Beaſt. Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is by ſome late and ſound Expoſitours concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be that Throne; and we have ſeene it pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led downe in <hi>Scotland;</hi> darkned in <hi>England.</hi> Yea, may not a ſtrict obſerver ſee the beginnings of diſſolution and breakings, in the very Kingdome of the beaſt it ſelfe?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2 41.42.</note> Doe not the <hi>toes of the feet</hi> of the image diſcover themſelves to be <hi>part iron and part clay?</hi> the <hi>clay,</hi> the people, wearyed and worne out with the weight, and hardneſſe, and rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the iron, <hi>i. e.</hi> papall tyranny and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, beginne to uncloſe and crumble off from them.</p>
               <p>Seventhly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34 44.45.</note> May we not ſee the <hi>ſtone cut off the mountaine without hands, i. e.</hi> the Kingdome of Chriſt, ſcorned and trampled on: but yet firme and ſtrong, as a ſtone, growing bigger and bigger toward a mountaine? Thus hath Reformation both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> hitherto proceeded. Its beginnings were at firſt contemptible, and knew no other name but ſedition, faction, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; yet, as it were <hi>without hands,</hi> by rare, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, and unexpected providences, beyond what we were able to aske or thinke, they have ſtood, and proſpered.</p>
               <p>Now are not theſe the <hi>buds and tender leaves of the figures,</hi> whereby we may conclude the ſummer
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112624:16"/>is nigh? May we not ſay with our Saviour, <hi>When you ſee all theſe things, know that it is neere even at the doores?</hi> Are not theſe hopefull ſignes, that the day of the Churches Redemption drawes nigh? May we not ſalute the Church as the Spirit doth, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Who is ſhe that looketh forth as the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning?</hi> Are not theſe the mornings of deliverance? Sure if our ſins doe not blaſt theſe bloſſomes and <hi>Hinder good things from us,</hi> we ſhall ſoone reape the fruite of our prayers. We dare not limit the holy one of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> but though <hi>the children are come to their birth,</hi> he may delay the time of bringing forth, or make us pay deare for theſe mercies. We may ſuffer many throwes and pangs, but we will ſay as <hi>Joſhuah, Numb.</hi> 14.8. <hi>If the Lord delight in us, he will bring us into this good land.</hi> If we were fit for it, we ſhould now ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the earth.</p>
               <p>Our third point is, <hi>It is the duty of all that make mention of the Lord, to give him no reſt till he make Jeruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi> Which we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to handle by way of application to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer point.</p>
               <p>We ſee <hi>Zion</hi> hath right to glorious mercies; theſe mercies are reſerved for theſe latter times. God hath not left us without ſome comfortable hopes, that the worke is now begun: theſe things have beene cleared to us.</p>
               <p>The next thing will be ſeaſonable to ſhew what God requires of us, what we muſt doe to obtaine theſe bleſſings: The Prophet tels us we muſt <hi>Give
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112624:17"/>him no reſt.</hi> For the handling this, we ſhall ſhew,</p>
               <p n="1">1. What we muſt doe to make God reſtleſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In what manner it muſt be done.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſubject of our worke, the things to be laboured for, which will make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the earth, and ſo conclude.</p>
               <p n="1">1 What muſt we doe that God may have no reſt?</p>
               <p>Firſt, We muſt pray earneſtly, fervently, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly. Prayer workes upon him, an engine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by himſelfe, to over-come himſelfe, a cord to binde himſelfe, a ſtrength that he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to yeeld to, yea, an authority that he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to obey: <hi>Concerning the worke of my hands, command ye me, Eſay</hi> 45.11. Prayer will over-rule God to any thing that is for our good: It will bow downe his eare, pull his hand out of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, his ſword out of his ſheath againſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, put up his ſword when it is drawne againſt his people: The Lord is at the call of his peoples prayers, <hi>Nigh unto all them that call upon him, Pſall</hi> 145.18. Yea, to doe for them what ever they aske, <hi>He will fulfill the deſire of them that feare him,</hi> ver. 19. Ready to doe for them, and as large in doing, he will doe all, ſatisfie their deſires.</p>
               <p>Prayer is the worke of Gods Spirit in us, and therefore cannot be in vaine. Faithfull prayer was never loſt, nor never ſhall while God is true. We have had experience of the power of it. It hath ſtrangely produced meanes, qualifyed, and fitted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112624:17"/>meanes, wonderfully protected meanes, united meanes, proſpered meanes, wrought through dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, diſcovered and defeated deſignes. If we ceaſe not begging, God will not ceaſe giving. <hi>While Moſes hands are held up Iſrael muſt prevaile.</hi> Therefore you <hi>that make mention of Gods name,</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule that profeſſes the Lord Jeſus, pray; you that have any intereſt in a God, improve it now; you that ever found the ſweetneſſe of prayer, pray now; if ever you ſeriouſly tooke the name of God into your mouthes, ſet to the worke now: pray for life, for liberties, for Religion, ordinances; for pretious peace, for <hi>eſtabliſhing</hi> and <hi>perfecting mercies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Difficulties are in the way; if we continue beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, God muſt yeeld; if we be not weary of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he muſt be weary of denying:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.6.</note> We hope there are many of <hi>Jacobs generation</hi> in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Let us reſolve to lay hold of God, to wraſtle with him, and not to let him goe, till he hath given us the bleſſing. If we have <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, we ſhall have his ſucceſſe, and amongſt other mercies, enjoy this, <hi>See the face of</hi> our King, <hi>as the face of God,</hi> as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaw the face of his brother.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, As we muſt pray, ſo we muſt doe; worke in prayer, and worke with prayer. Our prayer muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>James</hi> 5.16. <hi>working prayer:</hi> We muſt <hi>Pray without ceaſing,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Semper or are, eſt ſemper operari. Aug.</hi> To pray alwayes, is to follow our prayers with our hands, and to be alwayes in our actions, what we are in our prayers: it is not all the ſenſe of the place, but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112624:18"/>a good gloſſe. God loves to ſee our prayers live in our deeds. It is unbeleefe, baſe feare, or worſe; hypocriſie, to ſay to God in private, what we will not act in publicke. We ſhould ſhew more faith and ſincerity in our petitions, if we would faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully endevour what we aske, and ſooner obtaine an anſwer of our deſires. And this is a way to give God no reſt.</p>
               <p>If God be bound to attend the prayers of his people, much more their actions and labours that are for him: For there is more of himſelfe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and laid out in his ſervants paines, more faith, more zeale, more gifts, more wiſdome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the hazard of their perſons, eſtates, liberties, and lives, if the worke be (as they are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) dangerous and difficult.</p>
               <p>Therefore as we muſt <hi>watch unto prayer;</hi> ſo muſt we all, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7. eſpecially <hi>watchmen,</hi> men of publicke place, watch, labour, travaile, never <hi>hold their peace,</hi> conſult, ſpeake, write, doe all that their place gives them leave to doe, for the repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of <hi>Zions</hi> breaches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Davids</hi> counſell to <hi>Solomon</hi> is ſeaſonable, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 22.16. <hi>Ariſe therefore and be doing, and the Lord be with thee,</hi> While we are working for him, he will not be abſent, they may be ſure of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and ſo of aſſiſtance, and ſucceſſe, that ſet their hands to the worke of the Lord.</p>
               <p>If yet any ſhall thinke that this branch of our inſtruction doth not naturally flow from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Prophet here, <hi>Give him no reſt;</hi> yet let him conſider the former verſe, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112624:18"/>action: and withall, that he handle this, not onely as a diſtinct point, but as application of the former point: ſo the ingraffing this inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>to doe,</hi> is reaſonable, as I conceive, in the other reſpect, it is naturall.</p>
               <p>Secondly, But how muſt we pray and worke, ſo as God may be affected and have no reſt? Thats our ſecond thing, and for our direction in it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, We muſt be ſuch, whoſe perſons are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and qualified. Such the Prophet calls to the worke as <hi>make mention of the Lord,</hi> ſuch they had need to be, men that make mention of the <hi>Lord in Truth,</hi> men of particular intereſt in God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 48.1.</note> and ſpeciall acquaintance with him. As for wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, their <hi>Prayers are an abomination,</hi> and ſo are all their ſervices, God cares not for the helpe of his enemies. Such as are admirted to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent worke of the Lord, had need be holy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will have often occaſion to come into his preſence for aſſiſtance, counſell, direction, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement; and <hi>God will be ſanctified of all thoſe that draw neare to him.</hi> God ſmote <hi>Uzzah</hi> for lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hand upon the Arke, for want of a Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and ceremoniall holineſſe: how much more diſpleaſing will it be for men to intrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelſes upon Gods worke without true and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all holineſſe: you cannot worke for God, nor from God, except you be in God; not from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſtrength, nor to divine ends; and ſo will want comfort and ſucceſſe. You are to conflict
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112624:19"/>with ſpirituall enemies, To <hi>wraſtle with Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, Powers, the Rulers of the darkneſſe of this world, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high places,</hi> that I may allude to that of the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.12. And therefore you had need of <hi>ſpirituall wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons.</hi> You are to helpe build a <hi>ſpirituall houſe,</hi> ſo the Church is called, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. And therefore need ſpirituall tooles. You have Church-worke, as well as Common-wealth-worke, to remove ſuperſtition as well as oppreſſion; How can you tender the conſciences of others, if your owne conſciences be not tender? How will you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide <hi>ſincere milke of the word</hi> for poore <hi>babes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.3.</note> that cry to you, if you have not <hi>taſted that the Lord is gracious?</hi> You had need be as patriots of your Country, ſo friends of Chriſt, and <hi>children of the Kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Otherwiſe, if God ſhould proſper the worke in your hands, and inable you to build up <hi>a mountaine, of holineſſe,</hi> you would effect that, which when you have done, you could not affect. Or doe, as it is ſaid of them that built <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, that they periſhed in the flood; you may ſaye a poore King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from ſhipwracke, and periſh in the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the world. Grace is honourable, and fits men for the moſt honourable ſervice. We may ſay of parts and learning, that <hi>they have done vertuouſly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.29.</note> but Grace <hi>excelleth them all.</hi> This is the firſt, Men that will give him no reſt, muſt be men that know him, and are knowne of him: he will receive petitions by hands of them in office to him, by ſervants and Secretaries.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:112624:19"/>
               <p>Secondly, They that will give God no reſt, muſt pray and worke in faith. Faith workes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his promiſe, and ſo prevailes with him. It is very powerfull, <hi>James</hi> 5.15. <hi>The prayer of Faith ſhall ſave the ſicke.</hi> Faith hath a ſtrange faculty to knocke at Gods doore, yea, at his breaſt, goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his preſence, plead, and reaſon with him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire an account of his Promiſe, Power, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; <hi>Where is thy promiſe in which thou cauſedſt me to truſt?</hi> Yea, to dive into his bowels, and ſearch into them; <hi>Where are thy bowels?</hi> Faith is as neceſſary in working as in praying. Faith is mighty, yea, can doe what God can doe. To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve is difficult, but to him that beleeves,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.20.</note> 
                  <hi>nothing is impoſsible. If ye have faith as a graine of muſtard ſeed, ye ſhall ſay unto this mountaine, Remove hence to yonder place; and it ſhall remove. And nothing ſhall be unpoſsible unto you.</hi> Faith as a graine of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard-ſeed, <hi>parva, humilis,</hi> ſmall, of no account; but it muſt be as Muſtard-ſeed, <hi>acris, fervida;</hi> it muſt be lively, have acrimony and vivacity, and then it may remove mountaines. It is an Hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole, and here is the ſumme of it; what ever may be to the glory of God, or the good of his Church, be it never ſo difficult, Faith will effect it. Yea, a little active faith ſhall doe great things, a <hi>graine</hi> remove a <hi>mountaine.</hi> Although things be as ſtout and unyeelding as mountaines, as ſtrong and firme as mountaines, as ancient as the everlaſting hils, yet faith may remove them, if they ſtand in the way of Gods glory. You may read of the nobleacts of Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. Amongſt other won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112624:20"/>in ver. 33. <hi>By Faith men overcame Kingdomes.</hi> If faith could conquer Kingdomes, can it not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Kingdomes, and reforme them? Faith workes by that power that accounts <hi>the Nations as a deep of a Bucket,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.15.</note> as the ſmall duſt of the ballance,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>take up the Iſles as a very little thing.</hi> Therefore in all your great conſultations act in faith.</p>
               <p>Faith will keepe you to a rule, and ſo make you exact in juſtice: Faith will waite upon God for a command, and ſo will never be found in any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warranted courſe. It ſaith as <hi>Moſes</hi> to God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.15. <hi>If thy preſence goe not with me, carry us not hence,</hi> Faith will have a finger of direction, and then doubts not of a hand of protection. It will have a word of precept, and then diſtruſts not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of promiſe.</p>
               <p>Faith will goe forth in no ſtrength but Gods; not in the ſtrength of parts, policy, or multitude; as <hi>David</hi> went out againſt the <hi>Philiſtine,</hi> not with ſword, ſpeare, and ſhield, <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I come againſt thee in the name of the Lord of Hoaſtes.</hi> See now he couches himſelfe under this name of God by Faith, when he was beſet with dangers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>It is better ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uſt in the Lord, then to put confidence in Princes.</hi> He makes a wiſe choyce. Princes may erre and faile, but Ile take part with God and his cauſe: being thus reſolved for God rather then men, though Princes, he propoſes his enemies, ver. 10. <hi>All Nations com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me about.</hi> No leſſe then <hi>Nations</hi> againſt buth, yea <hi>all Nations,</hi> and they <hi>compaſsing him about.</hi> Well, let the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he knew whom he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112624:20"/>
                  <hi>In the name of the Lord will I deſtroy them.</hi> They come upon him againe with renewed ſtrength, and malice, ver. 11. <hi>They compaſſed me about, yea, they compaſſed me about;</hi> he kept to his firſt ſtrength, <hi>In the name of the Lord will I deſtroy them.</hi> His adverſaries are more inraged, ver. 12. <hi>They compaſſed me about as Bees.</hi> Bees for multitude, winged with fury, armed with weapons, ſtings; yet they could not afright nor weary his faith: his old ſhield was ſure, <hi>For in the name of the Lord I will deſtroy them.</hi> Faith would make us impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, invincible. Take therefore <hi>Davids</hi> reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in another place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.67. <hi>I will not truſt in my bow, neither ſhall my ſword ſave me. But thou haſt ſaved us from our enemies, and haſt put them to ſhame that hated us.</hi> Faith onely can furniſh you with weapons fit for thoſe you have to deale with. Your adverſaries are Antichriſtian, they that will deale with ſuch, muſt come armed with <hi>the blood of the Lamb, and the word of their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Apoc.</hi> 12.11. And faith onely knowes how to uſe theſe. You ſhould carry the blood of the Lambe alwaies about you, weare it in your hearts, and thinke you have to doe with the enemies of that Chriſt that ſhed his blood for you, againſt thoſe that trample that blood under their feet by their ſuperſtition and prophaneneſſe, ſuch as are bloody enemies, that thirſt for the blood of Saints.</p>
               <p>Faith will ſtrengthen your hearts by the Word of God, and aſſure you, that in all your paines, you worke in the belly of a promiſe, and what
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112624:21"/>you doe is to make God faithfull; you are doing that which he hath promiſed to doe himſelfe, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Sonne, and pull downe his enemies. You want eſtabliſhing mercies: <hi>If you will not beleeve, you ſhall not be eſtabliſhed, Iſay</hi> 7.9. You want con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering mercies: <hi>This is the victory that overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the world, even your Faith.</hi> Nothing can ſtand againſt Faith, <hi>Reſiſt the devill</hi> (ſtedfaſt in Faith) <hi>and he will flye from you.</hi> If God give more faith, we need not feare more difficulties. We may ſay as <hi>Paul, I can doe all things through Chriſt that ſtrengtheneth me, Philip.</hi> 4.13. Dye under enemies, or live to conquer them. Therefore <hi>beleeve and you ſhall ſee the glory of God; Joh.</hi> 11.40. and <hi>Jera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, If you would give God no reſt, you muſt in praying and doing quit your ſelves, and ſeeke the glory of God and the good of the Church.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you muſt not ſeeke your ſelves. Selfe is too baſe and low a thing to move a God with; as at all times, ſo now eſpecially, ſelfe muſt be below your thoughts, and not worth your meaneſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations; You eſpecially I ſpeake to, whom God hath taken up into the mount, as <hi>Moſes,</hi> to doe his buſineſſe, and to bring to us juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous lawes; You muſt now doe as the Church is exhorted to doe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.10, 11. <hi>Forget thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe,</hi> thinke not of raiſing your eſtates, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing your ſelves or your poſterity; <hi>So ſhall the King greatly deſire thy beauty,</hi> The King of heaven
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112624:21"/>will take pleaſure in you, and he will make the King on earth delight in you. Would you over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come difficulties without? labour firſt to overcome your ſelves. You can doe nothing great and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, ſo long as ſelfe hath any power in you. Selfe and ſiniſter ends would blaſt and undermine your conſultations, and divide you into as many wayes as you are men, <hi>(If every man ſhould ſeeke his owne, and not the things of Ieſus Chriſt:)</hi> which would be a miſcheife that hell it ſelfe could not parallel; to ſpeake our thoughts, we feare no treaſon but ſelfe. If you continue all to ſeeke the glory of God, you will be too ſtrong for any power either to divide or breake. The firſt ſtep of <hi>Iſraels</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance was <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtepping out of him ſelfe: <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.24, 25, 26. <hi>He refuſed to be called the ſonne of Pharaohs daughter.</hi> God would not imploy him till he had learned to refuſe Court offers; <hi>Chuſing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon.</hi> A good patterne for publike perſons; rather be poore with honeſty and a good cauſe, then riſe by Apoſtaſy. And had he not continued faithfull and conſtant in ſelfe-denyall, <hi>Iſrael</hi> had beene loſt. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.10. It was a hard pull. God was angry and would have conſumed <hi>Iſrael;</hi> there was nothing lay in the way but <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſincerity and faithfulneſſe to the cauſe. If he could be wrought off, the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was at an end. God himſelfe tries him, <hi>Let me alone, &amp;c. and I will make of thee a great Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> I will make thee great, and raiſe thy houſe to a Nation. But <hi>Moſes</hi> is deafe to ſuch offers, he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112624:22"/>will not be taken off ſo, he purſues his worke faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, nothing will ſerve him but <hi>Iſraels</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: ſuch faithfulneſſe to the cauſe of God had you need have. The Apoſtle tels us, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. <hi>They that will be rich, fall into temptation, and aſnare, and into many fooliſh and hurtfull luſts, which drowne men in perdition and deſtruction.</hi> If you will be rich or great, you will have temptations, and fall and drowne too in perdition. You, and Cauſe, and Kingdome, and all will drowne and periſh, if ſelfe-ends bias you. <hi>Saul</hi> went right a while, till faire <hi>Agag,</hi> and the fat of <hi>Amaleh</hi> lay in his way, till a rich booty turned him from his obedience, ſee the ſtory 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. and the dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of it. What ever pretence he had for his ſinne, in ſparing thoſe wicked enemies of the Church, that the people would have it, and it was for ſacrifice; yet ſaith <hi>Samuel</hi> to him, ver. 26. <hi>Thou haſt rejected the Word of the Lord, and the Lord hath rejected thee from being King over Iſrael.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people, nor falſe piety, nor pity, can excuſe neglect of Juſtice in Governours. If you would doe great things for God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 40.5.</note> you muſt not now <hi>ſeeke great things for your ſelves.</hi> Indeed you muſt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the world and your ſelves. You had need be more then men, ſuch as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was, your worke is like his, to <hi>pull downe mountaines, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt vallies, to make crooked things ſtraight, and rough things ſmooth.</hi> And as he had, ſo you have to deale with a <hi>generation of Vipers.</hi> Now our Saviour ſhewes by way of queſtion, what he was not, and what he was, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.7, 8, 9. <hi>What went you
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112624:22"/>out to ſee? a reed ſhaken with the wind?</hi> No, he was no light unſtable man, that would fluctuate and vacillate at every wind of threatning greatneſſe. <hi>What went you out to ſee? A man cloathed in ſoft ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> No, <hi>ſuch they are in Kings houſes. John</hi> was no ſuch man: he could not ſuite <hi>Herods</hi> humour, nor flatter his ſinnes. He would not alter his habit of Camels haire, the Court could not change him. <hi>What then went you out to ſee? a Prophet? Yea, I ſay more then a Prophet.</hi> Such ſhould you be, neither ſhaken with threatnings, nor won by ſoftneſſe, men ſtedfaſt in juſtice, yea Counſellers, and more then Counſellers.</p>
               <p>As you may not ſeeke your ſelves, ſo you muſt ſeeke the honour of God: that's the way to be more then men in our actions, to be divine in our ends. All other ends are too low for the meaneſt man, much more for ſo great a Councell. This is the way to prevaile with God: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he readily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces any propoſition this way. If any man have a deſigne to advance his name; what ever be the impediments, it muſt proſper: for you cannot have a thought this way, but God will ſecond it. He can as ſoone deſert himſelfe, as thoſe that worke for his glory. If you find any thing that may exalt his Majeſty, and he give you a heart faithfully to deſire it, be it what, or where it will, you need not deſpaire: though it lye under moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Kingdomes, you ſhall <hi>threſh them</hi> to duſt:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.15.</note> though it be buryed under Nations, and Empires, cuſtomes; antiquities, he will <hi>drive the Nations u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, ſcatter the everlaſting hils,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.6.</note> nothing ſhall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112624:23"/>ſtand in his way: where ere he findes his glory, he will ſeiſe upon it; and if they yeeld not ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it will coſt them deare. For he hath ſaid, <hi>Mine honour will I not give unto another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeke the good of <hi>Zion,</hi> this is the next to his glory, yea his glory is in <hi>Zion,</hi> there hath he put his name. This is a ſure way to move him: all that you can ſay or doe for his Church, is acceptable to him. What good deſignes come into your heads, are they for <hi>Irelands</hi> helpe, for the reliefe of his people, there or here? goe and preſent it to God firſt. See what his thoughts are <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.20. <hi>Is Ephraim my deare ſonne? is he a pleaſant childe? ſince I ſpake againſt him, I doe earneſtly remember him ſtill; therefore my bowels are troubled for him: I will ſurely have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Is it for my deare people in Ireland you pray and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? for my pleaſant children in England? I was angry, but I remember them ſtill, you did well to put me in mind, come, I will doe any thing for them. Oh! carry the Churches miſcries and diſtractions continually in your boſomes. That made the Prophet ſo earneſt and claborate, v. 1. <hi>For Zions ſake I will not hold my peace.</hi> We have an excellent patterne of a publicke ſpirit in <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 137.5, 6. <hi>If I forget thee, O Jeruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning: if I doe not remember thee, let my tongue cleave to the roofe of my mouth, if I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre not Jeruſalem before my chiefe joy.</hi> If my right hand doe not act its utmoſt for the Church, let it never act more; if my tongue doe not ſpeake what is for the good of the Church, may it cleave
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112624:23"/>to the roofe of my mouth: may my eſtate waſte and conſume, my parts be blaſted, my wiſdome be turned to folly, my time be nothing but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, if I doe not imploy all for the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches good. Looke above your ſelves to Gods glory, and his Churches good, and then God and you drive one deſigne: you ſhall be <hi>co-workers</hi> with God; when it is too hard for you, you may expect his helpe: doe you but what you can, it is his owne buſineſſe, he will doe the reſt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, If you would give God no reſt, you muſt be bold, a bold begger will prevaile.</p>
               <p>Let us breake in upon Gods retirings, thruſt our petitions into his eares, challenge mercy from him, urge his promiſes. God himſelfe hath war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted and allowed boldneſſe in prayer, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.12 <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. And none fare better then ſuch beggers. God admits his people to a ſtrange height of boldneſſe, to an impudency, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.8. ſome read it (and the word ſignifies ſo) <hi>propter improbitatem,</hi> as if we might be unmannerly with God in a holy affection to his glory and his Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches good. <hi>Let me goe,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Jacob, Jacob</hi> ſaith, no, <hi>Thou ſhalt not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As we muſt be bold in prayer with God, ſo bold and couragious in our actions towards men. It is ſaid of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>An honourable Counſeller; hewent in boldly to Pilate, and begged the body of Jeſus.</hi> And he did like an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Counſeller, that durſt ſay and doe what he thought to be right and juſt: he hazarded all in a good cauſe when it was at worſt: he would
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112624:24"/>owne Chriſt crucifyed. What favour he ſhewed to him being a condemned perſon, the law would interpret a juſtifying of his crimes, and an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to authority and Juſtice, and yet he boldly did it; and if he had not beene bold in it, he might have loſt it. Courage hath an excellent power in it: it alone will doe great things, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.13. A company of Rulers were aſtoniſhed by the zeale of the Apoſtles. The Text ſaies, <hi>When they ſaw the boldneſſe of Peter and John, and that they were unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, they marvelled, and tooke knowledge of them, that they had beene with Jeſus:</hi> As if boldneſſe had ſomething of the image of Chriſt in it: and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely it hath a Majeſty in it; the Rulers were at their wits end, ver. 16. <hi>What ſhall we doe to theſe men?</hi> zeale vanquiſhes where it comes, it is like the <hi>Sword of Jonathan and Saul,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.22.</note> that returnes not empty.</hi> And without this, other gifts and vertues are uſeleſſe. Feare diſables us for what we might doe, robs us of the meanes we have, and is a trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to all great deſignes. Therefore God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands courage in <hi>Joſhua, Joſh.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Be ſtrong and of a good courage:</hi> charged upon him againe in ver. 9. and by the people, ver. 18. as if the weight of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> lay upon this one grace, Courage. I will leave the Counſell with you that <hi>Joab</hi> gave his brother <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> They had a juſt cauſe, and ſo true courage and valour will be imployed,
<note place="margin">Pet. Mar.</note> 
                  <hi>Non ut inferantur, ſed ut propul ſentur injuriae,</hi> not to inflict but remove oppreſſion. <hi>Be of good courage, let us play the men, for our people, and the Cities of our God,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.12. The argument is ſtrong, it is for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:112624:24"/>
                  <hi>your people,</hi> and <hi>for the Cities of our God,</hi> for your people, as the Common-wealth, and Gods Cities as the Church, be valiant for both.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, If you would give God no reſt you muſt pray againſt denials, worke againſt diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, perſevere in both. What ever difficulties you meete with, <hi>Give him no reſt.</hi> Be conſtant in the duty what ever God ſaith, put by his deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, take no refuſals; the more denyals he gives, the more ſtrength you muſt get, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Aske and ye ſhall have:</hi> if that be too weake and doe not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, then <hi>Seeke,</hi> with more earneſtneſſe, <hi>and you ſhall find:</hi> if that faile, then <hi>Knocke,</hi> with more bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>and it ſhall be opened to you.</hi> This was the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of that poore woman, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.22. <hi>&amp;c. Have mercy on me thou ſonne of David, my Daughter is grievouſly vexed with a devill. He anſwered not aword.</hi> She cries after him: at laſt he ſaid, <hi>I am not ſent but to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael:</hi> ſhe leaves out the <hi>Sonne of David,</hi> and now <hi>Lord</hi> onely, <hi>Lord helpe me.</hi> What a Lord, and can helpe none but <hi>Iſrael?</hi> a Lord, and thy power confined? He ſeemes angry, and anſwers, <hi>It is not meete to give the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens bread to dogs.</hi> She riſes higher, and lockes her ſelfe within his denyall; <hi>Truth Lord, yet the dogges eate of the crumbes which fall from their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters table.</hi> She pleads his truth and juſtice: if mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy will not ſerve, let thy words be true, I am a dogge, yet there is ſomething for dogges, let me but have a dogges portion, crumbes, I crave no more.</p>
               <p>So ſhould we in praying and working: difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:112624:25"/>ſhould raiſe our ſpirits:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> wraſtled in the night, that was one diſcouragement; he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that was another; God was leaving of him, <hi>Let me goe;</hi> God ſtaid to his loſſe, <hi>He ſmote his thigh,</hi> yet he wraſtled upon one legge. So muſt you continue wraſtling with difficulties; If in the night of ſome calamity, if alone in that night, if God ſhould ſeeme to depart, yea, though he ſhould ſtrike and leave you maimed, halting, yet continue in the ſervice. Your valour and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have beene tryed, now your conſtancy, and patience is aymed at. Chriſt ſaith; we muſt pray alwayes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.1.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>non defatigari, faint not, non evadere</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, beginne well and end ill, <hi>begin in the ſpirit and end in the fleſh.</hi> To urge you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, I might urge your ſufferings; it was <hi>Pauls</hi> argument to the <hi>Galatians, Gal.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Have you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſo many things in vaine? if it be yet in vaine.</hi> If you ſhould now be weary and faint, before you be eſtabliſhed, you would loſe all your ſufferings, and the fruite of your long and great paines. As your owne ſufferings, ſo let Gods mercy ingage you to conſtancy. It is the ſame Apoſtles argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Having received mercy, faint not:</hi> God hath preſerved you, covered you under his wings, doe not therefore let your hearts ſinke under your great burthens. Or may that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment move with you, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. <hi>Be ye ſtedfaſt and unmoveable, alwayes abounding in the worke of the Lord, for as much as you know that your labour is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi> The good that you have done is not ſmall, although not anſwerable to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:112624:25"/>your deſires: Preſerving a Kingdome from ruine. We may ſay with the Prophet,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Except the Lord had left us ſuch a remnant, we had beene as Sodome, and we ſhould have beene like unto Gomorrah,</hi> ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up of ſinne and miſery. Beſides the ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the light, larger diſpenſing of the Word, freedome from innovations: All of theſe preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mercies, and many more, have beene the fruite of your watchfull care and paines. If we had no gaine here, yet God would reward you hereafter: Therefore <hi>be ſtedfaſt and unmoveable, your labour is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſtancy will conquer God and man. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> overcame God, <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.10, 11. &amp;c. they cryed to him when they were oppreſſed, he upbraided them with former mercies, ſaid flatly, <hi>I will deliver you no more.</hi> Nay, which was worſe, bids them <hi>Goe to their Gods whom they had ſerved, let them deliver them.</hi> God that uſes to give libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and upbraid none, here he gives nothing but upbraidings. They are not beaten off by this, but reforme he more exactly, renew their ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Doe what thou wilt with us, <hi>what ſeemes good unto thee, Onely deliver us this day. q d.</hi> What no more mercy? muſt we ſuffer? then doe what thou wilt: Let us ſuffer under thy hands, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us from theſe <hi>Ammonites:</hi> we never was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch cruell enemies as theſe, deliver us this day. In ver. 16. his Soule was grieved, he was wearyed, broken by their importunity. Goe on to ſeeke God, he cannot hold out long; prayers and importunities will breake his heart, extort,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112624:26"/>and force mercy from him: we have wearyed him by ſinne, let us weary him by prayer: We have beene impudent in tranſgreſſion, be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in ſeeking deliverance: We have beene bent to perpetuall backe-ſliding, let us be as conſtant in ſuing for deliverance, and ſo we ſhall be as <hi>Jacob; As a Prince haſt thou power with God, and with men, and haſt prevailed, Gen.</hi> 32.28. If it prevailes with God, with men much more.</p>
               <p>By this conſtancy of importunity, <hi>Dalilah</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Sampſon, Judg.</hi> 16. She deſired to know where his ſtrength lay; he deceived her, and mocked her divers times, at laſt ſhee urged him cloſe, ver. 15. <hi>How canſt thou ſay, I love thee, when thy heart is not with me? And ſhe preſſed him daily with her words, and his Soule was vexed unto death.</hi> ver. 16. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.8. <hi>Though he will not riſe and give, becauſe he is his friend, yet becauſe of his impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity he will riſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Amicus ille quod petebatur fecit, quia alter in petendo non defecit,</hi> Aug.</note> and give as many as he needeth.</hi> Where neither love, nor reaſon, nor deſert will gaine, importunity will make reſtleſſe. Hold out Worthies; <hi>Jacob</hi> had his wages denyed ten times, God paid him at laſt largely; ſo will he you, if you continue, waite patiently, be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt: The Kingdome is in a tottering condition, ſtedfaſtneſſe muſt beginne in your breaſts. Let me conclude this with <hi>Pauls</hi> words to the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.8. <hi>England</hi> may uſe them to You, <hi>We live if you ſtand faſt in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, If you would give God no reſt, you muſt take none. The beſt way to make God reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, is to be reſtleſſe in ſeeking, our activity
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:112624:26"/>workes upon God. <hi>Abraham</hi> had a hot ſervice of it to quench the wrath of God kindled againſt Sodome, and he was early at it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.27. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> when he had praying worke in hand, <hi>Early will I ſeeke thee, Pſal.</hi> 63.1. When he had workes of juſtice in hand, he would diſpatch it, <hi>I will ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy all the wicked of the Land, that I may cut off all wicked doers from the City of the Lord, Pſalm.</hi> 101.8. When he had Church-worke in hand, <hi>I will not give ſleepe to mine eyes, nor ſlumber to mine eye-lids, untill I finde a place for the Lord, an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation for the mighty God of Jacob, Pſalm.</hi> 132.4, 5. You muſt be reſtleſſe till <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> reſt, and be eſtabliſhed. We are ſorry we muſt require ſuch paines of you, but glad to ſee your chearefull and indefatigable travaile. God that cals you to it, makes you willing and able for it. Remember you are watchmen, and they muſt <hi>not hold their peace, night nor day.</hi> Your waking is our ſleepe, your toyle, our eaſe, your trouble our peace.</p>
               <p>You are like <hi>Gideons</hi> three hundred, <hi>Judg.</hi> 7.5. <hi>that lapped water with their tongues, as a dogge lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, Tanquam canis è Nilo; carptim, curſim;</hi> ſo doe you, injoy your repaſts as <hi>Jonathan</hi> purſuing his enemies, <hi>a little honey with the end of a rod,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.43. Goe on, Worthies, be yet more active, more heavenly, leſſe earthy. If you want com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, looke up to God and behold him, ſaying, <hi>Well done good and faithfull ſervants.</hi> Let action be your reſt, let it be your meate and drinke to doe the will of God: God cannot reſt till you give over working, he will worke with you ſo long as you worke for him.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:112624:27"/>
               <p>Seventhly, If you would give him no reſt, you muſt aske and deſire largely of him for his Church. God hath large thoughts toward <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Call unto me and I will anſwer thee, and ſhew thee great and mighty things which thou knoweſt not Jer.</hi> 33.3. God will doe for his people <hi>abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly above all that we can aske or thinke of, Epheſ.</hi> 3.20 Beyond your prayers and thoughts, much more beyond your indevours. God hath given in more in ſome things then was aymed at, and is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to out-goe any that are imployed for his Church. Carve as largely as you will to <hi>Zion,</hi> God will adde as much more: he is reſolved no Creature ſhall equall him in love to his Church.</p>
               <p>Take heed of being low ſpirited for God, of haltings and halvings in Reformation: Wee have ſeene the miſchiefes of ſuch a way already; yea, many times we loſe all, becauſe we would be contented with ſome.</p>
               <p>The Prophet was angry with <hi>Joaſh,</hi> that when he was to ſmite the <hi>Syrians,</hi> he ſmote but thrice, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 13.18, 19. God honours and proſpers them that doe all his will: <hi>Jehu</hi> did much, was very zealous, but the Text ſayes, <hi>He tooke not heed to walke in the Law of the Lord God of Iſrael with all his heart; For he departed not from the ſinne of Jeroboam,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10.31. And the evill effect it had is noted in the next verſ. 32. <hi>In thoſe dayes the Lord began to cut Iſrael ſhort.</hi> The ſame meaſure that you mete to him, he will mete to you; as you ſow in <hi>ſpirituals,</hi> you ſhall reape in <hi>carnals;</hi> if you
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:112624:27"/>cut Reformation ſhort, he will cut your priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and the Kingdomes peace ſhort: It is ſafe and ſucceſſefull to aime at great matters for God. We may thankefully imbrace what we can get, but ſeeke no leſſe than perfection: <hi>Magna audent quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam magni ſunt, &amp; qua audent obtinent. Bern.</hi> They that are truely noble and magnanimous they will attempt great things for God, and what they doe attempt they ſhall obtaine. Thinke of no leſſe then making <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the earth: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire not to ſee her in all her beauty and bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. In outward things, uſe your diſcretion, be as moderate as you ſee cauſe, but in the cauſe of God, <hi>Moſes</hi> his reſolution is worth imitation, he would not leave a <hi>hoofe behinde him.</hi> In this caſe <hi>Jehoſhophat</hi> gives good Counſell to his Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the Lord write it in your hearts, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6. <hi>Take heed what you doe, for you judge not for man, but for the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Wherein ſhould this labour be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſhall be your remembrance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> onely for two things; Doe them, and God will doe the reſt, To make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the Earth.</p>
               <p>Firſt, You muſt ſet up light. This is (as you have heard, a chiefe pait of the Churches beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; advance the light of powerfull Preaching, and that will advance the Truth, Religion, Peace, Chriſt, and all. The Hieroglyphicke of life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Egyptians</hi> was light, a burning lampe: and though ignorance be the Mother of Romiſh devotion, ſuch lampes are the life of Religion, powerfull Preaching.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:112624:28"/>
               <p>It was the worke of ſome to doe all they could to put out the light, the moſt horrid, helliſh, and unnaturall wickedneſſe that can be, to deny men the joy and comfort of our ſoules: the more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious they were in ſuppreſſing of it, the more paines muſt be taken in freeing of it. You have done much this way, and intend more; our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall joyne with your indevours, <hi>That the Word may runne and be glorified,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.1. That it may be ſaid of <hi>England</hi> as it was of <hi>Antioch, Act.</hi> 13.49. <hi>The Word of the Lord was publiſhed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Region.</hi> Nothing ſo excellent, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are diſpleaſed with it: The light is offenſure to ſore eyes.</p>
               <p>Some complained of <hi>Prometheus</hi> for reaching the uſe of fire, as the Poets ſay, and many amongſt us Preach againſt Preaching; But they that quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with the light,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48.</note> quarrell with Chriſt himſelfe, who is the <hi>Light of the Gentiles.</hi> Men complaine againſt the Seers; as <hi>Iſay</hi> 30.10, 11. <hi>See not, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie not right things;</hi> But their anger is againſt him that ſent them; let them ſpeake out, and they ſay, <hi>Cauſe the holy One of Iſrael to ceaſe from before us.</hi> The light it ſelfe ſtands in the light of their wicked wayes, as the Angell in <hi>Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ms</hi> way to his ſinne, and that's the reaſon <hi>They hate the light, becauſe their workes are evill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Men father diviſions upon the light, when as the preſent diſtractions and miſtakes are, becauſe it is but halfe day, the miſt is not quite diſpelled; Darkeneſſe cauſes diviſions, and thoſe moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, as quarrels in the night: The more <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:112624:28"/>and <hi>Teachers,</hi> and the <hi>Worke of the Miniſtery,</hi> the nearer we <hi>come to the unity of the Faith.</hi> Let light ſcatter, and it will pull downe the Kingdome of darkneſſe. You, and the Truth, and Chriſt have no ſuch enemy as ignorance.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Advance holineſſe. This is another winning and prevailing bleſſing. Oh that <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe might be as waves of the Sea!</hi> And then our <hi>Peace</hi> will be as <hi>a River, Iſay</hi> 48.18. Labor for holy Laws, holy worſhip, holy Sabbaths, holy families. For a holy Court, and then holineſſe will be in faſhion. For holy Univerſities, and then they will be filled, not with ſonnes of <hi>Beliall,</hi> but with ſons of the Prophets. But above all for a holy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, <hi>From the Prophets of Jeruſalem, is prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe gone forth into all the Land, Jer.</hi> 23.15. and from them muſt the people learne holineſſe. And a holy Magiſtracy, if God would <hi>reſtore our Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as at firſt;</hi> Let us injoy faithfull <hi>Moſeſes, Joſhua's, &amp;c. Then ſhould we be called the City of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the faithfull City, Iſay</hi> 1.26. Nothing but ſinne can hurt us, and ſinne will not onely make all your good purpoſes of Reformation abortive, but Gods too, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.9, 10. <hi>At what inſtant I ſay concerning a Nation and Kingdome, to build and plant it, if it doe evill in my ſight, that it obey not my voyce, then will I repent of the good wherewith I ſaid I would benefit it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seeke firſt the Kingdome of God in light,</hi> and <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> and <hi>then all other things ſhall be adminiſtred unto you.</hi> What ever difficulties hinder the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, let theſe be firſt in your intentions.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:112624:29"/>
               <p>Theſe directions God hath given you by me a weake creature, I hope you need not much to quicken you.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.9.</note> We deſire with <hi>Deborah</hi> to bleſſe the Lord that made <hi>the governours of Iſrael to offer themſelves willingly.</hi> Remember the place God hath called you to: the Kingdome is in a broken and ſhatterd condition, you are our watchmen, we ſay to you as <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Hobab, Num.</hi> 10.31. in the Wilderneſſe, thou art <hi>to us inſtead of eyes:</hi> you are our eyes to ſee our dangers, and our hands to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend us from them. We cannot better expreſſe that truſt that lies upon you then God himſelfe hath done concerning <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 4.16. <hi>thou ſhalt be to him inſtead of a God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Governours are ſtiled Gods in Scripture, but thoſe beſt deſerve it that are delivering rulers ſuch was <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſuch to us inſtead of a God are you; and then thinke you what Wiſdome, juſtice, firmneſſe, and ſtability is required in you.</p>
               <p>The truſt is heavy, our expectations great, and the account will be dreadfull. If you were alone in this worke you would ſinke under it, but God hath promiſed his preſence, <hi>and God is in you of a truth. It is the ſword of the Lord and the ſword of Gideon:</hi> Gods people ſee it with comfort, his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall feele it with ſhame. What the people obſerved of <hi>Ionathan,</hi> we may obſerve in you, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.45. <hi>he hath wrought with God this day;</hi> ſo you have, and ſo you will, we hope: and then <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliels</hi> words will hold, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.39. <hi>if it be of God you cannot overthrow it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:112624:29"/>
               <p>You labor with God, and for God, becauſe you labour for <hi>Zion;</hi> you travaile for her that travailed with you; For the Church that muſt ſtand and proſper, Chriſt hath promiſed, <hi>the gates of hell ſhall not prevayle againſt her;</hi> not the <hi>gate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in which was their ſtrength; in the <hi>gates</hi> the elders ſat, and ſo their polity as well as their ſtrength was in the gates; yet both ſhall not prevayle againſt the Church.</p>
               <p>God is gone before you <hi>travailing in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſtrength,</hi> challenging countries,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.1.</note> and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he ſaith, <hi>I will divide Shechem, mete out the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Succoth; Gilead is mine, over Edom will I caſt out my ſhooe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.6.7.8. And the prayers of Gods people are gone like the Arke before the campe of <hi>Iſrael, three dayes journey to ſeeke out a reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place, Num.</hi> 10.33. they are before you, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring your way, hewing downe difficulties: It is ſafe following ſuch a conduct: And God hath <hi>made the people willing in the day of his power.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.3.</note> That of the Pſalmiſt is conſiderable, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 47.9. <hi>The Princes of the people are gathered together:</hi> the marginall lection is, <hi>the voluntary of the people,</hi> the generous of the people: God hath the hearts of all men in his hand; <hi>And the ſhields of the earth belong unto the Lord:</hi> The <hi>Militia</hi> of the world is his: And all theſe ſhall ſecond them that ſeeke his glory and <hi>Zions</hi> Peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therefore proceed chearefully to make uſe of this ſweete opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to honour God, and heale our breaches. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven we hope is bigge with bleſſings; The Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112624:30"/>of God, is comming downe to dwell with men; what ever darke clouds appeare, let us continue praying, waiting, labouring, beleeving, God will at laſt <hi>eſtabliſh, and make Jeruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:112624:30"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die Mercurii</hi> 29. <hi>Junii.</hi> 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>IT is this day Ordered by the</hi> Commons <hi>now Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in</hi> Parliament, <hi>that Sir</hi> Thomas Barring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>doe returne thankes to Mr.</hi> Sedgwicke, <hi>for the great paines he tooke in the Sermon he Preacht this day at</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Margarets <hi>Church in</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>at the intreaty of the</hi> Commons Houſe of Parliament, <hi>this being the day of the publicke Faſt, And that he be deſired to Print his Sermon, And that no man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to Print it, but ſuch as he ſhall appoint, till the Houſe ſhall take further Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
               <signed>I appoint <hi>John Bellamy</hi> and <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> to Print my Sermon. WILLIAM SEDGVVICKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
